I have survived the [music] world's
unhealthiest diet and it almost killed
me. This is actually a confession. I
consumed, and I'm not kidding, 12 donuts
without even the thought that it was
going to affect my blood sugar. I didn't
even know about blood sugar at the time.
Now, of course, if I did that now, I
would just be a basket case. But my
entire childhood was filled with sugar,
starch, seed oils, sweetened cereals
every single morning. Every Halloween, I
would consume the entire amount of candy
that I had that night. At social events,
oh my gosh, I would consume a case of
soda. I would do chicken papies, like
four of them. And in addition to that, I
would have TV dinners. And every single
night after dinner, I would literally
graze from the time I would stop dinner
until the time I was ready to go to bed.
It was a constant grazing every single
night. And then when I was 16, I worked
at the movie theater, okay? I was the
popcorn maker and I would come home with
garbage bags filled with popcorn. And so
my dad and I would sit there and watch
TV and just graze and down so much
popcorn. It was crazy. I was in the
military. I went through basic training.
Ate more junk food, refined foods, a lot
of stress, no sleep. Then I went into
college, more stress, lots of coffee,
lots of junk food. Of course, they were
all deep fried carbs and seed oil, but
that's what I was living on. And of
course, then came the ulcers. I had
liver problems. I had gallbladder
problems. I didn't know at the time
that's what it was. But I had this very
full, tight, painful feeling underneath
my right rib cage that referred to my
right shoulder. I had no idea that was
my liver. But after the years of eating
the huge bags of Doritos,
I said, you know, I'm going to eat
healthy when I graduate. That was my
justification. I remember after I
graduated in practice, I would have a
pint of Ben and Jerry's ice cream every
single night before I went to bed. And I
always wondered why did I get restless
leg syndrome? That was a severe B1
deficiency. I didn't know at the time.
There I was nervous and jittery and I
had to get the energy out. And of course
then came the insomnia. My eyelids were
on fire. It was like sandpaper in my
eyelids and very very sticky and dry.
That was a severe blood sugar issue. I
had severe arthritis down my spine and
my fingers. I got kidney stones. And you
would think with all those problems I
would change my ways. I would try but I
would fail. I finally weighed 211bs.
The food that I was eating was not
really satisfying me. That problem was
something completely different. It was
dopamine hunger. Dopamine is stimulated
with a lot of refined carbs and sugar
keeping these dopamine spikes going on
and on and on. Dopamine is not a
pleasure neurotransmitter. It's a
neurotransmitter that causes drive and
anticipation for something. It's
something that your body learns from to
want more and more of it, but it's not
the thing that gives you the pleasure.
The problem is it's a trap. Because as
this drive for more junk food occurs,
you get less pleasure from it to the
point where the feedback loop sends a
signal back telling the body to make
more and more and more dopamine. What
happens over time if you eat a lot of
junk food or you have too much dopamine,
you start getting resistance and that
little receptor for dopamine gets sucked
into the cell to the point where you
have fewer receptors. So now we have
dopamine dysregulation. We have a
problem with dopamine and this is what's
behind addictions. Okay? And I had a
severe addiction to junk food and
refined carbs. And this is why
ultrarocessed foods initially taste good
and they satisfy you for a little bit,
but probably an hour, an hour and a half
later, you now are hungry, but you're
not really hungry. You have this
neurotransmitter that's kicked in there
causing you to want that same thing over
and over and over again. It's really a
trap. And if you have this dopamine
problem and you go back to real food, it
doesn't give you the same sensation
because your receptors are all messed up
and there's confusion in the brain. So
you just want more junk food to get more
of this. So that mechanism was literally
training me to go off track and want the
wrong foods. So now let's talk about how
to solve this problem because the first
thing you need to do is identify the
real enemy. The real enemy
is this.
It's your environment. Because our food
system has been completely engineered
for addiction. As soon as you're
stressed, tired, or somewhat hungry
because your blood sugar is off, you
will not be able to have willpower. I
don't care how hard you try, you're
going to cave eventually. It's kind of
like giving an alcoholic a job at a
liquor store. They're going to end up
drinking that alcohol. I mean, look what
happens when you go into a grocery
store. You have aisles of pure refined
carbohydrate junk snacks. When you're
hungry or tired, you will walk out with
junk food. I guarantee. Recently, I went
into people's houses doing videos on
trying to teach them about what to eat.
And I go in the refrigerators and I go
in their pantry and I see the same thing
over and over and over again. Just so
much junk food. And they're in an
environment where they are exposed to it
constantly. And there's certain health
experts that keep giving this advice.
You just got to try harder. everything
in moderation. You just have to have
willpower. It's all about calories. Just
eat less. It's portion control, right?
Take a look at Weight Watchers. What is
their success rate? It's like 95%
failure because they're trying to
motivate people. The enemy is not a lack
of willpower. It's your environment.
We're living in this modern world which
is a trap with so many things engineered
to keep us hooked and addicted. Removing
you from all the triggers is really the
only solution. That way all these
options are not available. There's only
one option and it's a healthy food.
Let's go through step by step what you
need to do to get out of the trap and
focus on the environment first. Number
one, clean out all of the ultrarocessed
foods out of your entire house. I'm
talking about your refrigerator and your
pantry. It's been making you sick. It's
the stuff that causes disease and
diabetes. It's not helping you. And to
have this food in the house is not a
good strategy. It's going to keep you
going off track all the time. Now, I'm
going to put a little link down below
and at the end of this video, you can go
to it and you can download a free app.
It's Dr. Berg Junk Food Meter to be able
to scan these different foods one by
one. So, you can really quickly
determine what is ultrarocessed foods.
Alterprocessed foods are really mostly
made of three ingredients: seed oils,
industrial starches, and sugars. If you
think about it, what's missing from
those ingredients? Protein. And then
also foods that are not as calorie dense
that take work to break down and digest
and that would be vegetables or like a
salad, right? Veggies because protein
will help your blood sugar and really
truly satisfy you and it's loaded with
nutrition as well. Okay, so this is
number one. Number two, absolutely
positively no snacking. Why? because
we're trying to correct insulin and
every time you eat, no matter if it's
healthy or not, you spike insulin. And
so both of these will help reverse the
insulin damage. Grazing at night is the
worst time to snack. So you should
literally after dinner, turn the lights
off, put a sign there, the kitchen is
closed, so that way you can
overemphasize. You don't want to be
grazing after dinner. You want to be
able to eat and then not eat until the
next day. Number three, no food visible.
So many people on their countertops,
they have these little bowls of food.
Sometimes they're healthy food. I would
not keep that food out there. Keep all
this food in the refrigerator or the
pantry where you cannot see it because
just the visual cues are going to
trigger dopamine. Number four,
substitute foods. There are so many
recipes for the things that people
crave. I have a whole channel on this. I
will put a link down below. So that way
you can at least have substitute foods
to gradually come off your addictions.
I'm sorry, your junk foods. All right.
Number five, no blue light at night. The
screens, the computers, the cell phones,
that gives off blue light. And you
should probably get a monitor that
filters out a lot of this blue light,
but the blue light severely interferes
with your sleep cycles. If you're not
sleeping, what's going to happen is your
blood sugar is going to cause you to
want to graze or eat the wrong things.
So many people eat junk food because
they're tired because they didn't sleep.
Number six, the grocery store. Make it a
personal
rule that you never go to the grocery
store unless you're fed first and you
have a list of foods you're going to
get. Don't be just going there mindless
just looking around. Hm, what should I
buy? What am I in the mood for? Because
you're not asking your real self. You're
asking your dopamine self and it's going
to give you the wrong answer. When you
go in that grocery store, okay, here's
the grocery store. Go around the
perimeter, okay? Don't go inside. That's
where they have most of the junk food.
Of course, they have the junk food when
you check out, too. But this facility is
a trap. This is where people cave and
they buy the wrong things and then they
bring it home and they have to keep
saying no over and over and over again.
I have finally gotten out of the trap
when I go to the grocery store. Boy, I
do not buy anything that's not on the
list that I bring in there. But as I'm
going through the grocery store, I'm
looking around and I'm seeing these
people what they're buying and I'm like
I'm not saying anything, but I'm like,
"Wow, boy, I can see you have a spike in
dopamine." Number seven, preserve your
sleep. Sleep greatly helps stabilize
your blood sugar and reduces cravings.
big time. Number eight, social events.
This is a killer right here. It's such a
social natural thing to give people
sweets and certain foods that maybe they
shouldn't eat and maybe even go there
and bring some food to share and then
that way you can have something to fall
back on. So many times I've been to
social events where they didn't have
anything I could eat at all and that was
a problem. do what you can to be more in
control of this environment right here
and try to limit the damage control
that's going to happen when you go to
some of these social events. Some people
as part of their work, boy, they go to a
lot of social events and they have to go
out to dinner a lot. But you can
personally be a trends setter and maybe
have the social event at your house
where you can then control the